### Muhammad N. Naseem, CCM

Phone: (786) 797-5328 Email: nabeelnasim@gmail.com

#### **SUMMARY**

An enthusiastic self-motivated and result oriented Civil Engineer with over eight years of experience in construction management & inspection, quality control & assurance and document control of various infrastructures projects in the NY metro area.

### **EDUCATION**

- MS. Construction Management, Florida International University, Miami, Florida 2013
- BS in Urban Engineering, NED University of Engineering & Technology-Karachi, Pakistan -2011

### CERTIFICATION

- CCM Certificate # 5335 2017
- OSHA 10 &30 Hours
- OSHA-40 Hours HAZWOPER
- ACI Concrete Construction Technology Course (CCTC)
- ACI Concrete Field Testing Technician Grade I
- ACI Concrete Construction Special Inspector(CCSI)
- OSHA Confined Space Entry
- DDC Water main Training

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

NYCDDC/NYCDEP Flushing Creek Green Infrastructure Program REI - Office Engineer (March 2021-Present)

Providing construction inspection services for dozens of green infrastructure improvements along sidewalks and streets in the Fresh Meadows, Kew Gardens, and Flushing neighborhoods of Queens, NY, under a New York City Department of Design and Construction (NYCDDC) contract. The project, which is part of the New York City Department of Environmental Protection (NYCDEP) program to address combined sewer overflows (CSOs) in the Flushing Creek catchment, includes the installation of bioswales, rain gardens, green streets, and stormwater infiltration basins and inlets. Other project elements include sidewalk reconstruction, re-striping of pavement and crosswalks, landscaping, and maintenance and protection of traffic (MPT) planning. Mr. Naseem collaborated with the NYCDEP to produce work orders for contractors and tracked those contractors' performance and completion of work orders. Managing submittals and RFI's, preparing change orders, reviewed inspectors' daily reports, prepared monthly progress payment approvals, and tracked item quantities for overruns and underruns. Cost Analysis, creating master schedule and tracking milestones and analysis, ensuring project quality, monitoring project scope changes, handling weekly progress meetings, critical phase meetings and project delivery meetings. Mr. Naseem also prepared meeting minutes and assisted in project closeouts. Handling punch list, substantial and final completion, QA/QC final reports. Ensuring budget management and Value Engineering. Resolving critical phase issues ensuring no delays in project delivery.

NYCDDC REI Services for Prior Notice Sidewalks in Brooklyn – Senior Inspector (March 2020 – March 2021) Provided office engineering services under a requirements contract with the New York City Department of Design and Construction (NYCDDC) for REI services for improvements to sidewalks in Brooklyn, Queens, and Manhattan, NY, that are determined to violate New York City Department of Transportation (NYCDOT) and ADA

guidelines. The scope of work for this \$25 million project includes the removal of concrete; subgrade excavation and compaction; construction of new sidewalks, driveways, curbs, and pedestrian ramps; maintenance of traffic; community outreach; and coordination with agencies and utilities. Mr. Naseem collaborated with the NYCDOT to produce work orders for contractors and tracked those contractors' performance and completion of work orders. He prepared change orders, reviewed inspectors' daily reports, prepared monthly progress payment approvals, and tracked item quantities for overruns and underruns. Cost Analysis, creating master schedule and tracking milestones and analysis, ensuring project quality, monitoring project scope changes, handling weekly progress meetings, critical phase meetings and project delivery meetings. Mr. Naseem also prepared meeting minutes and assisted in project closeouts. Handling punch list, substantial and final completion, QA/QC final reports.

NYCDDC REI Services for Prior Notice Sidewalks – Office Engineer (Jan 2019- March 2020) Provided office engineering services under a requirements contract with the New York City Department of Design and Construction (NYCDDC) for REI services for improvements to sidewalks in Brooklyn, Queens, and Manhattan, NY, that are determined to violate New York City Department of Transportation (NYCDOT) and ADA guidelines. The scope of work for this \$9 million project includes the removal of concrete; subgrade excavation and compaction; construction of new sidewalks, driveways, curbs, and pedestrian ramps; maintenance of traffic; community outreach; and coordination with agencies and utilities. Mr. Naseem collaborated with the NYCDOT to produce work orders for contractors and tracked those contractors' performance and completion of work orders. He prepared change orders, reviewed inspectors' daily reports, prepared monthly progress payment approvals, and tracked item quantities for overruns and underruns. Cost Analysis, creating master schedule and tracking milestones and analysis, ensuring project quality, monitoring project scope changes, handling weekly progress meetings, critical phase meetings and project delivery meetings. Mr. Naseem also prepared meeting minutes and assisted in project closeouts. Handling punch list, substantial and final completion, QA/QC final reports.

# NYCDEP Installation of New Water Meters in NYCHA Buildings in Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx. (Jan 2018- December 2018)

**Senior Inspector** - Responsible for construction inspection/management & QA/QC for the contractor's operation. Coordinating with the inspectors, scheduling them for weekly work for various NYCHA buildings/sites. Reviewing Inspector's reports for the accuracy & compliance and daily work progress. Making sure site is safe and contractor is following NYCDEP specification and OSHA guidelines while performing the work. Coordinating with NYCHA, DEP and NYCHA plumbers for building water shutdowns. Requesting BWSO Street shutdown from DEP. Reviewing and approving reports on behalf of office engineer in e-Builder. Reviewing & approving as-built drawings. Preparing estimates and schedules for the work order. Preparing change orders for any additional work. Closing out job once any NYCHA facility is completed.

### NYCDDC, REI Services for the Construction of Storm and Sanitary Sewers and Water main in Amsterdam Ave, Staten Island, NY. (Jan 2017-Dec 2017)

**Senior Inspector** - This project involved the construction of a storm sewer, sanitary sewer and water main on Amsterdam Ave in Staten Island. Ancillary work on the site includes construction of a 24" reinforced concrete pipe (RCP) and 12" extra strength vitrified pipe (ESVP). Monitored contractor work per NYCDEP and NYCDOT specification while contractor doing construction of sanitary sewer, storm sewer, and highway construction respectively. Made sure that concrete tests were performed according to ACI standards. Prepared daily reports and sketches for work in progress, maintained site safety and ensuring MPT plans are implemented. Prepared inspection reports along with calculations

for quantities of materials. Responsible for writing daily work report and inspecting the excavation of structural and unclassified materials, and sub-base backfills. Inspected the compaction of select backfill materials and protective shoring in the trenches. Inspected the storm sewer pipe installation of RCP and ductile iron pipe (DIP), sanitary sewer pipe installation of an ESVP and RCP, and installation of catch basins type 1, 2, and 3. Inspected the installation of a fire department communication system, manhole, and electrical conduit & other electrical components, and the installation of manholes for both sanitary & storm water systems. Collected water samples and prepared Tap Cards and In-Service sheets on Visio. Also worked on PIMS to add the reports and quantities and helped in closeouts. Inspected pavement milling & paving for asphalt. The project had about 1286 LF of Storm Sewer, 10 catch basins, 540 LF of Sanitary Sewer, 1300 LF of 8" Water Main, 5 Fire Hydrants with five 6" Gate Valves and eight 8" Gate Valves.

## NYCDDC, REI Services for the Construction of Storm and Sanitary Sewers and Water main in Twombly Ave, Staten Island, NY. (Jan 2016-Dec 2016)

**Inspector** assigned to the installation of:

- Sanitary Sewers and Catch basins
- Replacement of 8"and 12" Water Mains
- Reconstruction of Curbs and Sidewalks as needed
- Restoration of Roadway

Inspected MPT for compliance of plans, excavation, sheeting, construction of chambers, installation of catch basins, new manholes, sewers, house connection, concrete cradle, backfilling and performed concrete test. My responsibilities included but not limited to assisting Resident Engineer, maintaining complete documentation, field measurements, estimate of quantities for payments, maintain and coordinate matters of construction issues with area residents, utility companies, NYCDOT, NYCDEP, and schools in the surrounding area. Also reviewed construction methods to ensure compliance, conformance and safety. Keeping excellent working report within the field office, resident engineer and other field staff. Also helped office engineer by creating tap cards and In-service sheet on Visio.

# NYCDDC, REI Services for the Construction of Storm and Sanitary Sewers and Water main in Wards Point Ave, Staten Island, NY. (Jan 2015-Dec 2015) - M&J Engineering, P.C

Inspector - This project involved the construction of a storm sewer, sanitary sewer and water main on Wards Point Ave in Staten Island. The work on site include construction of 3150 LF of 8" water main, water service connections, sanitary sewer, construction of 2500 LF of storm sewer and catch basins, construction of outfall structure on timber piles and construction of 2000 LF of 10" ESVP sanitary sewer. Monitored contractor work per NYCDEP and NYCDOT specification during the installation new sanitary sewer, storm sewer, and highway construction respectively. Performed the concrete tests according to ACI standards. Prepared daily reports and sketches for work in progress, maintained site safety and ensuring MPT plans are implemented. Prepared inspection reports with detailed calculations for quantities of materials. Inspected the compaction of select backfill materials and protective shoring in the trenches. Inspected the storm sewer pipe installation of RCP and ductile iron pipe (DIP), sanitary sewer pipe installation of an ESVP and RCP, and installation of catch basins type 1, 2, and 3. Collected water samples and prepared Tap cards and In-service sheets. Inspected trench excavation, milling & paving operation. Inspected the construction of house connections.

### Field Construction Engineer - Pennoni Associates (Jan 2014 – Jan 2015)

Client: Essex County

Project: Traffic Signal improvements at various locations on county roadways for Essex County

- Responsible for maintenance of safety on site as stipulated in various OSHA manuals.
- Maintaining daily field report according to FHWA standards which includes DC-29a and DC 70's.
- Interpretation of drawings and specification to construction staff.
- Concrete Testing according to ACI standards.
- Inspection of curbing, sidewalk, signs, guide railing, pavement markings, landscape items, traffic signals, maintenance and protection of traffic, highway lighting.
- Placement and review of MPT for lane enclosure
- Review/ analyze contractor's project schedule and interpretation of contract documents.

### **SPECIAL SKILLS**

- Working knowledge of the FHWA for federally funded projects.
- ADA guidelines for handicap ramps.
- ACI Field testing
- Experience in Land Surveying using Level, Theodolite, Total Station and GPS
- Working knowledge of RS Means cost estimating program
- NJSAT Certified Asphalt technologist

#### SOFTWARE PACKAGES

**Technical Software:** MS Project, AutoCAD Civil Design, TEKLA, REVIT, PIMS, e-Builder

Office Software: Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, Publisher, Power Point, Access and Outlook)

### REFERENCES

Will be furnished upon request.